A Guide to the Valerie Kitchens Papers, 1967-1992
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Valerie Kitchens Papers, 1967-1992
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 348
1 box.
Kitchens, Valerie B. (Valerie Berman), 1937-2013
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Arlington Historical Society in April 2014.
Biographical Information
Valerie B. Kitchens was a local activist for conservation, wildlife, parks, and other political issues that impacted Arlington County and Northern Virginia. Kitchens became an influential force in several conservation organizations, including as a board member for Friends of Arlington Parks and the Arlington Outdoor Education Association. Birding and ornithology remained a special passion of Kitchens throughout her life. Active in local bird watching groups, Kitchens served as President of the Northern Virginia Chapter of the Virginia Society of Ornithology. In broader local politics, Kitchens also was a part of the Arlingtonians for a Better County (ABC), a non-partisan organization that supports and campaigns for candidates for both the Arlington County Board and School Board, as well as other local issues.
Kitchens was born on January 24, 1937, in Cresskill, New Jersey to Otto and Eva Berman. In 1964, she earned a master's degree in Foreign Affairs from Georgetown University. In the same year, she married Allen H. Kitchens. They had two children, Sharon and Jeffrey. Kitchens passed away on February 16, 2013, in Arlington, Virginia.
Scope and Content
This small collection spans approximately .5 linear feet and dates from 1967-2010, with the bulk of materials dating from the late 1960s, as well as 1979-1992. The materials constitute a few records Valerie Kitchens saved from her involvement and membership in several conservation oriented groups, including the Arlington Outdoor Education Association, Audubon Naturalist Society, and Friends of Arlington Parks. Materials include newsletters, meeting minutes, agendas, correspondence, and as well as publications about local conservation issues. Additionally, there are papers Valerie and her husband, Allen, completed in the late 1960s recording use of bluebird houses for the Audubon Naturalist Society.
Arrangement
These materials were divided into five series based on subject matter. The first three contain records Valerie Kitchens used and created as a member of three organizations. Series 1 contains Kitchens directors file for the Arlington Outdoor Education Association. Series 2 holds materials related to Audubon Naturalist Society and Kitchens' ornithology related projects and writings. Series 3 covers her involvement with Friends of Arlington Parks. This series is divided into two subseries, one for newsletters (many of which Kitchens edited) and one for Kitchens' extant folder of meeting notes, which include minutes, agendas, correspondence, constitution, and bylaws. Series 4 holds several publications related to parks and conservation Kitchens used and Series 5, Subject Files, holds miscellaneous materials.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Records
Researchers particularly interested in Kitchens' involvement with the Arlington Outdoor Education Association may find that organization's records, housed in RG 111, Arlington Outdoor Education Association Records, particularly useful. Likewise, RG94, Arlingtonians for a Better County may include more details on Kitchens' work with ABC.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Parks -- Virginia; Outdoor education; Community organization.; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Arlington Outdoor Education Association
  - "AOEA [Valerie Kitchen's] Director File," 1984-1987 (1) (Box 1)
  - "AOEA [Valerie Kitchen's] Director File," 1984-1987 (2) (Box 1)
- Audubon Naturalist Society and Orinthology
  - Naturalist Notes Newsletters, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - "The Eastern Bluebird: An Endangered Species," by Valerie Kitchens, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Bluebird House Instructions and Project Questionnaires, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 1)
- Friends of Arlington Parks
  - Newsletters
    - 1979-1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Notes
    - "Meeting Notes," [Bylaws, Constitution, Correspondence, and Board List], 1979-1980, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
- Publications
  - Critical Environmental Areas, Virginia, December 1972 (Box 1)
  - The Nature Conservancy: 50 Years of Conservation in Virginia, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Potomac Overlook REgional Park Proposal, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Trail Guide, W&OD Regional Park, n.d. (Box 1)
- Subject Files
  - Clean Water bumper sticker (Box 1)
  - Meadowlark GArdens Regional Park brochure, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Ethics for Travelling Outdoorsmen, Outdoor Ethics Guild, 1967 (Box 1)